I'm speaking to you about what I call the "mesh."
أنا أحدثكم عن ما أسميه "الشبكة" (للأعمال المترابطة)
It's essentially a fundamental shift
إنه في الأساس تحول رئيسي
in our relationship with stuff, with the things in our lives.
في علاقتنا مع الأشياء المحيطة بنا في حياتنا
And it's starting to look at --
ويبدأ بالنظر في --
not always and not for everything --
ليس دائما وليس لكل شئ --
but in certain moments of time,
ولكنه في بعض الآوقات المعينة
access to certain kinds of goods and service
يصل إلى أنواع محددة من السلع والخدمات
will trump ownership of them.
ورقة رابحة لمن يمتلكه.
And so it's the pursuit of better things,
ولهذا فإن ملاحقة الأشياء الأفضل
easily shared.
هو الأسهل للمشاركة
And we come from a long tradition of sharing.
ونحن نأتي من عادات مشاركة طويلة
We've shared transportation.
فقد تشاركنا في المواصلات
We've shared wine and food
وتشاركنا في المشرب والمأكل
and other sorts of fabulous experiences
وتشاركنا في تجارب رائعة أخرى.
in coffee bars in Amsterdam.
في مقاهي أمستردام.
We've also shared other sorts of entertainment --
تشاركنا في أنواع أخرى من وسائل الترفيه
sports arenas, public parks,
الميادين الرياضية و الحدائق العامة
concert halls, libraries,
قاعات الحفلات و المكتبات
universities.
والجامعات
All these things are share-platforms,
لكل من هذه الآشياء نقاط تتشارك فيها،
but sharing ultimately starts and ends
ولكن في نهاية المطاف المشاركة تبدأ و تنتهي
with what I refer to
بما أشير إليها
as the "mother of all share-platforms."
على أنها الأم لكل مراحل المشاركة.
And as I think about the mesh
فكلما فكرت في الانسجام
and I think about, well, what's driving it,
وبما يحفزه
how come it's happening now,
وكيفية حدوثه الآن
I think there's a number of vectors
أعتقد بأن هنالك عدد من الأسباب
that I want to give you as background.
التي أود أن أعطيها لكم كخلفية.
One is the recession --
الأولى هي الركود
that the recession has caused us
لأن الركود جعلنا
to rethink our relationship
نعيد التفكير في علاقاتنا
with the things in our lives relative to the value --
مع الأشياء المتعلقة بالقيمة في حياتنا
so starting to align the value
فبدأت مواءمة القيمة
with the true cost.
مع التكلفة الحقيقية.
Secondly, population growth
ثاني الأسباب هو النمو السكاني
and density into cities.
والكثافة السكانية في المدن.
More people, smaller spaces,
عدد أكبر من الناس، مساحة أصغر
less stuff.
و أشياء أقل.
Climate change:
يتغير الطقس
we're trying to reduce the stress
ونحاول أن نقلل التوتر
in our personal lives and in our communities
في حياتنا الشخصية وفي مجتمعاتنا
and on the planet.
وفي كوكبنا.
Also, there's been this recent distrust
وهنالك أيضا عدم ثقة في الآونة الأخيرة
of big brands, global big brands,
بالعلامات التجارية الكبرى، العالمية منها
in a bunch of different industries,
في مجموعة من مختلف الصناعات
and that's created an opening.
وأدى هذا إلى فتح ثغرة.
Research is showing here, in the States,
تفيد الدراسات هنا في الولايات المتحدة
and in Canada and Western Europe,
وفي كندا وأوروبا الغربية
that most of us are much more open
أن معظمنا منفتح أكثر
to local companies,
للشركات المحلية
or brands that maybe we haven't heard of.
أو العلامات التجارية التي ربما لم نسمع عنها.
Whereas before, we went with the big brands
بينما في السابق، كنا نفضل العلامات التجارية الكبرى
that we were sure we trusted.
التي كنا متأكدين من أننا نثق بها.
And last is that
وآخر الاسباب هو
we're more connected now to more people on the planet
أننا متصلين الآن بعدد أكبر من الناس في كوكبنا
than ever before --
من أي وقت مضى--
except for if you're sitting next to someone.
إلا إذا كنت جالسا بالقرب من شخص ما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The other thing that's worth considering
الشئ الآخر الذي يجب وضعه بعين الاعتبار
is that we've made a huge investment
هو أننا استثمرنا بشكل كبير
over decades and decades,
لعقود وعقود،
and tens of billions of dollars
و عشرات المليارات من الدولارات
have gone into this investment
أنفقت على هذه المشاريع
that now is our inheritance.
والآن هذا هو إرثنا
It's a physical infrastructure
فهي بنية تحتية مادية
that allows us to get from point A to point B
تمكننا من الذهاب من النقطة أ إلى النقطة ب
and move things that way.
وتمكننا من تحريك الأشياء بنفس الطريقة.
It's also -- Web and mobile
مكننا الانترنت والهاتف النقال أيضا
allow us to be connected
من الاتصال ببعضنا البعض
and create all kinds of platforms and systems,
وشكل لنا مختلف الأنظمة والبرامج.
and the investment of those technologies
إن الاستثمار في هذه التقنيات
and that infrastructure
وهذه البنية التحتية
is really our inheritance.
هو إرثنا حقا.
It allows us to engage
فهو يمكننا من أن نتفاعل
in really new and interesting ways.
بطرق جديدة و وشيقة.
And so for me, a mesh company, the "classic" mesh company,
ولذلك فبالنسبة لي، فإن الشركة المنسجمة التقليدية
brings together these three things:
تضم هذه الأشياء الثلاثة:
our ability to connect to each other --
إمكانية الاتصال ببعضنا البعض
most of us are walking around with these mobile devices
ثانيا، معظمنا يتنقل حاملا معه جهازا نقالا
that are GPS-enabled and Web-enabled --
مزودة بنظام تحديد مواقع و انترنت
allows us to find each other
والتي تمكننا من العثور على بعضنا البعض
and find things in time and space.
والعثور على أشياء في الفضاء.
And third is that physical things
وثالثا، إن هذه الأشياء المادية
are readable on a map --
يمكن العثور عليها في الخريطة
so restaurants, a variety of venues,
فالمطاعم، ومختلف المواقع
but also with GPS and other technology
ولكن مع نظام تحديد المواقع و التقنيات الأخري
like RFID
مثل معلمات تردد الراديو "آر إف آي دي"
and it continues to expand beyond that,
فإنها تتوسع إلى أكثر من ذلك
we can also track things that are moving,
فنستطيع أن نتعقب الأشياء التي تتحرك
like a car, a taxicab, a transit system,
مثل السيارات و سيارات الأجرة ونظام الترانزيت
a box that's moving through time and space.
و الاشياء التي تشغل وقتا وحيزا.
And so that sets up
وهذا يجعل
for making access to get goods and services
الوصول إلى السلع والخدمات
more convenient and less costly in many cases
في معظم الأحيان، أكثر راحة وأقل كلفة
than owning them.
من امتلاكهم.
For example, I want to use Zipcar.
فعلى سبيل المثال، أريد استخدام موقع زيبكار
How many people here have experienced
كم شخصا هنا جرب
car-sharing or bike-sharing?
مشاركة سيارة أو دراجة؟
Wow, that's great. Okay, thank you.
مذهل، هذا جيد. شكرا لكم.
Basically Zipcar
في الأساس، زيبكار هي
is the largest car-sharing company in the world.
أكبر شركة لمشاركة السيارات في العالم.
They did not invent car-sharing.
هم لم يبتكروا مشاركة السيارات
Car-sharing was actually invented in Europe.
حيث أن مشاركة السيارات قد ابتكرت في أوروبا.
One of the founders went to Switzerland,
أحد مؤسسي زيبكار ذهب إلى سويسرا،
saw it implemented someplace,
ورأى الفكرة منفذة في مكان ما،
said, "Wow, that looks really cool.
وقال "مذهل، هذه الفكرة تبدوا رائعة حقا
I think we can do that in Cambridge,"
أعتقد أنه يكمننا تنفيذها في كامبريدج"
brought it to Cambridge
فجلب الفكرة إلى كامبريدج
and they started -- two women --
وبدأ رجلان بتنفيذها
Robin Chase being the other person who started it.
حيث أن روبن جيز كان الشخص الذي بدأها.
Zipcar got some really important things right.
حصلت زيبكار على بعض الأشياء المهمة بطريقة صحيحة.
First, they really understood
أولا، فهموا جيدا
that a brand is a voice and a product is a souvenir.
أن العلامة التجارية هي صوت، وأن المنتج هو تذكار.
And so they were very clever
وبهذا فقد كانوا أذكياء
about the way that they packaged car-sharing.
في الطريقة التي قدموا بها مشاركة السيارة.
They made it sexy. They made it fresh.
فقد جعلوها جذابة و جديدة
They made it aspirational.
جعلوها طريقة طموحة.
If you were a member of the club,
فلو أنك كنت عضوا في زيبكار
when you're a member of a club, you're a Zipster.
يلقبونك بــ زيبستر.
The cars they picked didn't look like ex-cop cars
لم تكن السيارات التي اختاروها تشبه سيارات الشرطة القديمة،
that were hollowed out or something.
التي تم تفريغها أو شئ من هذا القبيل.
They picked these sexy cars.
ولكنها كانت سيارات جذابة.
They targeted to universities.
استهدفوا الجامعات
They made sure that the demographic
وتأكدوا من أن الديموغرافية
for who they were targeting and the car was all matching.
لكل من السيارة و الاشخاص المستهدفين كانت متطابقة.
It was a very nice experience,
كانت تجربة رائعة.
and the cars were clean and reliable, and it all worked.
فقد كانت السيارات نظيفة وتعمل بطريقة جيدة
And so from a branding perspective, they got a lot right.
وبهذا فإنه من المنظور التسويقي، فقد حصلوا على أشياء كثيرة صحيحة.
But they understood fundamentally
ولكنهم فهموا بشكل أساسي
that they are not a car company.
بأنهم ليسوا مجرد شركة سيارات.
They understand that they are an information company.
فقد فهموا بأنهم شركة معلومات.
Because when we buy a car
لأنك عندما تشتري سيارة
we go to the dealer once, we have an interaction, and we're chow --
نذهب مرة واحدة إلى البائع، نتعامل معه، ثم نذهب
usually as quickly as possible.
في أسرع وقت ممكن عادة.
But when you're sharing a car and you have a car-share service,
ولكن عندما تتشارك السيارة وتحصل على خدمة مشاركة السيارة،
you might use an E.V. to commute,
يمكن أن تستخدم سيارة للتنقل
you get a truck because you're doing a home project.
أو الحصول على شاحنة لأنك تقوم بمشروع في البيت.
When you pick your aunt up at the airport, you get a sedan.
عندما تقوم بالمرور على عمتك فالمطار لتقلها تجلب سيارة سيدان.
And you're going to the mountains to ski,
وعندما تذهب للتزلج على الجبال،
you get different accessories put on the car
تأخذ معك مختلف الإكسسوارات في السيارة.
for doing that sort of thing.
للقيام بالتزلج.
Meanwhile, these guys are sitting back,
في هذه الأثناء، يقوم هؤلاء الناس
collecting all sorts of data
بجمع مختلف المعلومات
about our behavior and how we interact with the service.
عن تصرفاتنا وكيفية تعاملنا مع هذه الخدمات.
And so it's not only an option for them,
وهذا ليس خيارا لهم فقط،
but I believe it's an imperative
ولكنني أعتقد أنه ضرورة
for Zipcar and other mesh companies
لزيبكار و الشركات الشبكية الأخرى
to actually just wow us,
لإذهالنا فعلا،
to be like a concierge service.
لكي يكونوا كخدمة التوصيل الشخصي.
Because we give them so much information,
لأننا نعطيهم معلومات كثيرة،
and they are entitled to really see
ويجب عليهم في أن يروا فعلا
how it is that we're moving.
كيفية تنقلنا.
They're in really good shape to anticipate
فإنهم في وضع جيد لترقب وتوقع
what we're going to want next.
الشئ التالي الذي نريده.
And so what percent of the day
ما هي النسبة اليومية
do you think the average person uses a car?
التي تتوقعونها لاستخدام السيارة من قبل شخص عادي؟
What percentage of the time?
ما هي نسبة المئوية من الوقت؟
Any guesses?
هل هناك أي تخمينات ؟
Those are really very good.
هذا جيد جدا
I was imagining it was like
كنت أتخيلها على أنها
20 percent when I first started.
٢٠ بالمئة عندما بدأت.
The number across the U.S. and Western Europe
النسبة في الولايات المتحدة وأوروبا الغربية
is eight percent.
هو ٨ بالمئة.
And so basically even if you think it's 10 percent,
وبهذا فأنه حتى لو أنك تعتقد أنه ١٠ بالمئة،
90 percent of the time,
٩٠ بالمئة من الوقت،
something that costs us a lot of money --
الشئ الذي يكلفنا الكثير من المال
personally, and also we organize our cities around it
شخصيا، وننظم مدننا حوله،
and all sorts of things --
وكل هذه الاشياء
90 percent of the time it's sitting around.
٩٠ بالمئة من الوقت تحوم حولنا.
So for this reason,
لهذا السبب
I think one of the other themes with the mesh
أعتقد بأن أحد المواضيع الأخرى مع الشبكة ،
is essentially that, if we squeeze hard
هو بشكل أساسي، إذا ركزنا
on things that we've thrown away,
على الإشياء التي أهملناها،
there's a lot of value in those things.
هو وجود قيمة كبيرة في هذه الأشياء التي وضعناها جانبا.
What set up with Zipcar -- Zipcar started in 2000.
بدأت زيبكار في عام ٢٠٠٠
In the last year, 2010,
وفي العام الماضي، ٢٠١٠
two car companies started,
بدأت شركتين
one that's in the U.K. called WhipCar,
واحدة منهم في المملكة المتحدة وتدعى ويبكار
and the other one, RelayRides, in the U.S.
والأخرى تدعى ريلاي رايدز في الولايات المتحدة.
They're both peer-to-peer car-sharing services,
كلتا الشركتين تقدم خدمات مشاركة السيارة بين نظيرين،
because the two things that really work for car-sharing
لأن الشيئين الأساسيين لإنجاح مشاركة السيارة
is, one, the car has to be available,
هما أولا توفر السيارة،
and two, it's within one or two blocks
وثانيا وجودها ضمن حي أو اثنين
of where you stand.
من مكان تواجدك.
Well the car that's one or two blocks from your home or your office
السيارة التي تكون على بعد حي أو اثنين من مكان بيتك أو مكتبك،
is probably your neighbor's car,
هي غالبا سيارة جارك،
and it's probably also available.
وهي غالبا متوفرة أيضا.
So people have created this business.
ولهذا السبب ابتكر الناس هذا المشروع.
Zipcar started a decade earlier,
أنشأت زيبكار قبل عقد من الزمن
in 2000.
في عام ٢٠٠٠
It took them six years
وقد استغرقوا ٦ سنوات
to get 1,000 cars in service.
لإدراج ١٠٠٠ سيارة في الخدمة.
WhipCar, which started April of last year,
فيما أن ويبكار، التي أنشأت في ابريل من السنة الماضية
it took them six months
استغرقهم ٦ اشهر
to get 1,000 cars in the service.
لإدراج ١٠٠٠ سيارة في الخدمة.
So, really interesting.
إن هذا مثير للاهتمام فعلا .
People are making anywhere between
يجني الناس ما بين
200 and 700 dollars a month
٢٠٠ و ٧٠٠ دولار في الشهر
letting their neighbors use their car when they're not using it.
من جراء مشاركة سياراتهم مع جيرانهم.
So it's like vacation rentals for cars.
و هذا يشبه تأجير السيارات في الإجازات.
Since I'm here --
بما أنني هنا --
and I hope some people in the audience
وأرجو وجود عدد من الحضور
are in the car business --
الذين يعملون في قطاع السيارات
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
-- I'm thinking that, coming from the technology side of things --
اعتقد انه، نظرا من الجانب التقني للأشياء،
we saw cable-ready TVs
رأينا التلفزيونات المزودة بالكابل،
and WiFi-ready Notebooks --
والكمبيوترات المحمولة المزودة بالواي فاي،
it would be really great if, any minute now,
أعتقد بأنه من الجيد فعلا، في أي دقيقة الآن،
you guys could start rolling share-ready cars off.
أن تبدأوا تداول السيارات الجاهزة للمشاركة.
Because it just creates more flexibility.
لأن هذا يشكل انسيابية أكثر.
It allows us as owners to have other options.
ويمكننا كمالكين للحصول على خيارات أخرى
And I think we're going there anyway.
واعتقد بأننا نتجه إلى هذا الطريق على أية حال.
The opportunity and the challenge with mesh businesses --
إن الفرصة والتحدي مع أعمال الشبكة --
and those are businesses like Zipcar or Netflix
وتلك الأعمال مثل زيبكار أو نت فليكس
that are full mesh businesses,
التي هي كليةً أعمال شبكة
or other ones where you have a lot of the car companies,
أو شركات أخرى حيث لديك الكثير من شركات السيارات
car manufacturers,
ومصنعي السيارات
who are beginning to offer
الذين بدأوا بتقديم
their own car-share services
خدمات مشاركة سياراتهم
as well as a second flanker brand,
وكذلك كعلامات فلانكر
or as really a test, I think --
أو حقاً من قبيل الإختبار، --
is to make sharing irresistible.
لجعل التشارك لا يمكن مقاومته
We have experiences in our lives, certainly,
لقد خبرنا خلال حياتنا
when sharing has been irresistible.
حينما يصبح التشارك لا يمكن مقاومته
It's just, how do we make that recurrent
الأمر فقط حول كيفية تكرار ذلك
and scale it?
وتوسعته؟
We know also, because we're connected in social networks,
كما نعلم أيضاً، لأننا شبكات إجتماعية مترابطة
that it's easy to create delight
أنه ليس سهلاً صنع البهجة
in one little place.
في مكان صغير واحد
It's contagious because we're all connected to each other.
إنها كالعدوى لأننا جميعاً مترابطون مع بعضنا البعض
So if I have a terrific experience
لذا فلو كان لدي تجربة مروعة
and I tweet it, or I tell five people standing next to me, news travels.
وقمت بنشرها عبر تويتر، أو أخبرت خمسة أشخاص بقربي، ستنتشر الأخبار
The opposite, as we know, is also true,
والعكس كما نعلم، أيضاً صحيح
often more true.
وأكثر صحةً
So here we have LudoTruck, which is in L.A.,
لدينا هنا شركة لودو ترك، تقع في لوس أنجلوس
doing the things that gourmet food trucks do,
تقوم بالأشياء التي تفعلها شاحنات الغذاء الشهي
and they've gathered quite a following.
وقد جمعوا الكثير
In general, and maybe, again, it's because I'm a tech entrepreneur,
بصفة عامة، لأنني رائدة أعمال من قطاع التكنلوجيا
I look at things as platforms.
فأنا أرى الأشياء كمنصات
Platforms are invitations.
والمنصات هي دعوات للمشاركة
So creating Craigslist
اذاً إنشاء قوائم كريغ (Craigslist)
or iTunes and the iPhone developer network,
أو شبكات تطوير آي تيونز أو آي فون،
there are all these networks -- Facebook as well.
كل هذه الشبكات موجودة -- وكذلك الفيس بوك
These platforms invite all sorts of developers
هذه المنصات تدعو جميع أنواع المطورين
and all sorts of people
وكل أنواع البشر
to come with their ideas and their opportunity
ليقدموا افكارهم وفرصهم
to create and target an application
لإنشاء وإستهداف تطبيق
for a particular audience.
من أجل جمهور محدد
And honestly, it's full of surprises.
وبكل صراحة، فانها مليئة بالمفاجآت
Because I don't think any of us in this room
لأنني لا أعتقد أن أي شخص في هذه القاعة
could have predicted the sorts of applications
قد تنبأ بكل أنواع التطبيقات
that have happened at Facebook, around Facebook,
التي تقدم عبر الفيس بوك، وحوله
for example, two years ago,
كمثال، قبل عامين
when Mark announced
حينما أعلن مارك (صاحب الفيس بوك)
that they were going to go with a platform.
بأنهم سينطلقون عبر منصة تطوير
So in this way, I think that cities are platforms,
وبهذه الطريقة، أعتقد أن المدن عبارة عن منصات
and certainly Detroit is a platform.
وبالتحديد مدينة ديترويت هي منصة
The invitation of bringing
ودعوة إستجلاب
makers and artists and entrepreneurs --
صانعين وفنانين ورواد أعمال
it really helps stimulate this fiery creativity
ستساعد حقاً على إيقاد شعلة الإبداع
and helps a city to thrive.
وتساعد المدينة على الإزدهار
It's inviting participation,
فهي تدعو للمشاركة
and cities have, historically,
وللمدن خاصية تاريخية
invited all sorts of participation.
بدعوة كل أنواع المشاركة
Now we're saying that there's other options as well.
ونحن نقول بأن هناك خيارات أخرى أيضا
So, for example, city departments
كمثال، يمكن لإدارات المدينة
can open up transit data.
أن تفتتح ترانزيت للبيانات
Google has made available transit data API.
لقد أتاحت غوغل تطبيق API لترانزيت البيانات
And so there's about seven or eight cities already in the U.S.
كذلك فان هناك سبعة أو ثمان مدن أمريكية بالفعل
that have provided the transit data,
قدمت ترانزيت للبيانات
and different developers are building applications.
ويقوم مختلف المطورون ببناء تطبيقات جراء ذلك.
So I was having a coffee in Portland,
كنت أحتسي القهوة في بورتلاند
and half-of-a-latte in
ونصف الكوب مليئ
and the little board in the cafe
وفجأة بدأ المجلس المصغر
all of a sudden starts showing me
في المقهى بعرض معلومة
that the next bus is coming in three minutes
بأن الحافلة القادمة ستصل خلال 3 دقائق
and the train is coming in 16 minutes.
والقطار سيصل في غضون 16 دقيقة
And so it's reliable, real data
لذا فالأمر مأمون، وبيانات حقيقية
that's right in my face, where I am,
أمامي، حيث كنت أنا
so I can finish the latte.
ويمكنني إنهاء كوب القهوة
There's this fabulous opportunity we have across the U.S. now:
هناك فرصة مذهلة متوفرة لدينا في أمريكا الآن:
about 21 percent
حوالي 21%
of vacant commercial and industrial space.
من المساحات التجارية والصناعية فارغة
That space is not vital.
وذلك الفراغ ليس حيويا
The areas around it lack vitality
فالمنطقة حولها بحاجة للحماس
and vibrancy and engagement.
والإلتزام والمشاركة
There's this thing -- how many people here
هذا الشئ موجود -- كم شخص هنا
have heard of pop-up stores or pop-up shops?
قد سمع بمصطلحي محلات "بوب أب" و متاجر "بوب أب"؟ (موسمية)
Oh, great. So I'm a big fan of this.
حسناً. أنا معجبة جداً بهذين المفهومين
And this is a very mesh-y thing.
وهذا شئ شبكي للغاية
Essentially, there are all sorts
في الأساس هناك كل أنواع
of restaurants in Oakland, near where I live.
المطاعم في أوكلاند، قرب بيتي
There's a pop-up general store every three weeks,
وهناك محلات "بوب أب" كل 3 أسابيع
and they do a fantastic job
وهم يقومون بعمل رائع
of making a very social event
باقامة مناسبات إجتماعية للغاية
happening for foodies.
تقام لمشتري الأغذية
Super fun, and it happens in a very transitional neighborhood.
متعة كبيرة، وهي تحدث في كل حي وما بعده
Subsequent to that,
بعد ذلك
after it's been going for about a year now,
وقد أقيمت لما يقارب العام الآن
they actually started to lease and create and extend.
فقد بدأوا بالإقراض والإبداع والتوسعة
An area that was edgy-artsy
المنطقة التي كانت مبدعة
is now starting to become much cooler
بدأت تصبح الآن أكثر إبداعا
and engage a lot more people.
وتشرك المزيد من الناس
So this is an example.
هذا مثال
The Crafty Fox is this woman who's into crafts,
الثعلب الماكر هي هذه المرأة التي تبيع المصنوعات اليدوية
and she does these pop-up crafts fairs around London.
وهي تبيع هذه المصنوعات الـ "بوب أب" في منطقة لندن
But these sorts of things are happening
لكن هذه الأشياء تحدث
in many different environments.
في الكثير من البيئات المختلفة
From my perspective, one of the things pop-up stores do
في تصوري، أحد الأشياء التي تفعلها محلات الـ "بوب أب"
is create perishability and urgency.
هي أنها تنشئ نوع من العجلة والإلحاح
It creates two of the favorite words of any businessperson:
وهي تقدم كلمتين محبوبتين لأي مشتغل بالأعمال:
sold out.
قد تم بيعه
And the opportunity to really focus trust and attention
والفرصة للتركيز في الثقة و ان تنتبه
is a wonderful thing.
تجعلك مندهشا
So a lot of what we see in the mesh,
لذا فالكثير مما نراه في "الشبكة"
and a lot of what we have in the platform that we built
والكثير مما لدينا في المنصات التي بنيناها
allows us to define, refine and scale.
تتيح لنا أن نقدم التعريف، والتنقية والتوسعة.
It allows us to test things as an entrepreneur,
وهي تتيح لنا اختبار الأشياء كرواد أعمال
to go to market,
وأن نذهب الى السوق
to be in conversation with people,
وأن نشارك في حوار مع الناس
listen, refine something and go back.
ونستمع وننقي الشئ ونعود ادراجنا
It's very cost-effective,
انها فعالة من حيث الكلفة
and it's very mesh-y.
وهي شبكية للغاية
The infrastructure enables that.
فالبنية التحتية تسمح بذلك
In closing, and as we're moving towards the end,
في النهاية ، وبينما نمضي للختام
I just also want to encourage --
أريد أن أحث --
and I'm willing to share my failures as well,
وأريد أن أتقاسم إنتكاساتي أيضاً،
though not from the stage.
ولكن ليس من خشبة المسرح
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I would just like to say that one of the big things,
أرغب في قول شئ واحد كبير
when we look at waste
حينما ننظر للمخلفات
and when we look at ways that we can really be generous
وحينما ننظر للطرق التي يمكن أن نصبح عبرها كرماء
and contribute to each other,
ونساهم لبعضنا البعض
but also move to create a better economic situation
وكذلك نسعى لإنشاء أوضاع اقتصادية أفضل
and a better environmental situation,
ونحسّن البيئة
is by sharing failures.
فهذا سيكون عبر تشارك الإنتكاسات
And one quick example
مثال واحد سريع
is Velib, in 2007,
في فيليب عام 2007
came forward in Paris
جاء من باريس
with a very bold proposition,
مع مقترح جرئ جداً
a very big bike-sharing service.
وهو خدمة ضخمة لتشارك الدراجات
They made a lot of mistakes.
وقد قاموا بالكثير من الاخطاء
They had some number of big successes.
وحققوا العديد من النجاحات
But they were very transparent, or they had to be,
لكنهم كانوا شفافين للغاية، أو توجب عليهم
in the way that they exposed
إلى الحد الذي كشفوا عنه
what worked and didn't work.
عن ما نجح وما فشل
And so B.C. in Barcelona
وكذلك بي سي في برشلونة
and B-cycle
وبي- سايكل
and Boris Bikes in London --
ودراجات بوريس في لندن --
no one has had to repeat
لم يتوجب على أي منهم تكرار
the version 1.0 screw-ups
النموذج الأول من الأخطاء
and expensive learning exercises
وتكلفة تعلم التجارب باهظة الثمن
that happened in Paris.
التي حدثت في باريس
So the opportunity when we're connected
اذاً فالفرصة حينما نتواصل
is also to share failures and successes.
أيضاً لنتشارك الإنتكاسات والنجاحات
We're at the very beginning of something
ونحن على مشارف بداية شئ
that, what we're seeing
نحن نراه
and the way that mesh companies are coming forward,
والطريقة التي تتقدم بها شركات الشبكات
is inviting, it's engaging, but it's very early.
تدعونا، وتجعلنا نشارك، لكنها في بواكيرها الأولى
I have a website -- it's a directory --
لديّ موقع إلكتروني، وهو فهرس
and it started with about 1,200 companies,
وقد بدأ بحوالي 1200 شركة
and in the last two-and-a-half months
وخلال الشهرين والنصف الماضية
it's up to about 3,300 companies.
أرتفعت لحوالي 3300 شركة
And it grows on a very regular daily basis.
وهو يتنامى بوتيرة متسارعة
But it's very much at the beginning.
والموقع ما يزال في بداياته
So I just want to welcome all of you onto the ride.
لذا أريد أن أدعوكم جميعاً للمشاركة
And thank you very much.
وشكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)